Finding Aid for School of Public Health (University of Michigan) Records 1909-2015 (bulk 1941-2006).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
School of Public Health (University of Michigan) records
1909-2015
1941-2004
University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
8.74 GB online
97 linear feet in 98 boxes
Teaching and research unit of the University of Michigan. Records include dean's files, administrative records, minutes, also records of the school's program in Public Health Nursing and records of the Association of Schools of Public Health.
87321 Bimu C281 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was acquired in several accessions from 1971 to 1994 (Donor No. 1756 ). The records of the Public Health Nursing Program were received in 1977.
The records are open for research use with the exception of personnel-related files including search, review, promotion, and tenure files which are restricted for thirty years from date of creation, student educational records which are restricted for seventy-five years from date of creation, and records that fall under the Executive Officers closure policy.
Personnel Related Records -- Boxes 62-63 and 95-97
Student Academic Records -- Boxes 62-63 and 95-96
Executive Officers Records -- Boxes 64-94
The School of Public Health at the University of Michigan officially dates from 1941, but the university had been a pioneer in public health education since 1887. In that year the State Board of Health suggested that the university establish a professorship of hygiene. The Board of Regents appointed professors Victor Vaughan, Albert Prescott, and John Langley to devise a plan for the creation of a Department of Hygiene. The committee recommended the establishment of a department of hygiene and physiologic chemistry. The head of the department was to have the title Professor of Hygiene and Physiologic Chemistry and Director of the Hygiene Laboratory. The Regents approved the committee's suggestion and named Vaughan to head the new department.
The Hygienic Laboratory was established in 1889 and was the first laboratory of its kind in the country. It contained "all of the apparatus employed by Koch" and positioned the University of Michigan at the forefront of American bacteriological research. The laboratory was used for instruction in bacteriology, for research into the etiology of disease, and as a test site for food and drink suspected of contamination. The Regents' decision to finance the department was richly rewarded by the service provided and prestige garnered by the laboratory.
The first degree in hygiene was awarded in 1897. From 1897 to 1916 the master's degree in public health was offered through the Medical School. In 1911 the Regent's established the degree of Master of Science in Public Health and approved the curriculum and degree of Doctor of Public Health that same year. In 1916 the public health program was transferred to the graduate school. An effort by the Regents to coordinate all health sciences work on campus led to the creation of the Division of Hygiene and Public Health in 1921. Professor John Sundwall headed this division until 1941. In addition to the public health program, the division at various times included the University Health Service, the physical education program, and a number of courses taught in other schools and departments. In 1934 Michigan became the first university to offer an organized program in the field of medical care.
In 1939 the Board of Regents approved the creation of a School of Public Health and Preventive Medicine with the stipulation that "no addition to the budget of the Division of Hygiene and Public Health as adopted in 1939 would result from this action." The Rockefeller and W. K. Kellogg foundations provided grants of $500,000 each for operating expenses; this allowed the School of Public Health to begin offering classes in 1941-1942. Dr. Henry F. Vaughan, former Commissioner of Health in Detroit and the son of Victor Vaughan, was named the first dean of the School of Public Health in 1941. The grants also covered construction costs of the school's building on Observatory Road. The building was completed in 1943.
The school was initially organized in three departments: Public Health Practice, Epidemiology, and Environmental Health. The Department of Public Health Practice included the fields of public health administration, public health economics, health education, health nursing, public health dentistry, physiological chemistry, mental health, and nutrition. The Department of Epidemiology encompassed public health laboratory practice, immunology, and health statistics. The Environmental Health Department covered public health engineering and industrial health. The departments within the School of Public Health were not static; they changed in response to dynamics within the school, the university, and the world of public health. Divisions developed into departments, then declined; totally new departments were created, then meiotically divided into newer programs and departments. Among those developing were Departments of Tropical Diseases, Biostatistics, Population Planning, Community Health, Hospital Administration, and Medical Care Organization.
The school offered programs leading to master's and doctoral degrees in public health and to a bachelor's degree in public health nursing. In 1950, a grant from the W. K. Kellogg Foundation permitted the creation of an undergraduate degree program in public health aimed at meeting the increasing demand for personnel to serve as administrators and technicians in government public health agencies. In addition, the school sponsored frequent institutes and inservice programs for health workers, administrators, and public officials. As in the nineteenth century, the School of Public Health proved responsive in fulfilling its service obligation to Michigan.
From its inception, the School of Public Health has supported an active program of research. Thomas Francis, Jr., head of the Epidemiology Department, served as chairman of the Armed Forces Influenza Commission and directed the research at the school's Virus Laboratories that developed an influenza vaccine during World War II. Pearl Kendrick, a professor of epidemiology, did significant work in developing a vaccine effective against pertussis. Lowell Coggeshall, chairman of the Tropical Disease Department, conducted extensive studies on malaria control. The school is perhaps best known for its work on poliomyelitis. Under the direction of Francis, the school was the largest recipient of grant funds from the National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis (later known as the March of Dimes). Francis conducted numerous epidemiological studies and Jonas Salk began the work which led to the development of a polio vaccine. The field test of Salk's vaccine was directed by Francis, in what was the largest mass experiment in medicine ever undertaken.
The Bureau of Public Health Economics, established in 1945 under the direction of Nathan Sinai, carried on extensive studies of voluntary health insurance plans, developed an evaluation schedule for the programs of the World Health Organization, and surveyed the public health services of numerous states and communities. Myron Wegman, dean of the School of Public Health, likewise manifested an interest in the economics of health care provision through his work on health maintenance organizations. The school has worked closely with state and local health agencies, most notably through the field experience portion of the curriculum and the Kellogg Foundation-sponsored Michigan Community Health Program. The school's work in the Tecumseh Community Health Study provides a Michigan analog to the ongoing Framingham study of health and disease patterns in a community over time. In the mid-1970s the school also undertook pioneering research into the short and long-range effects of PBBs (polybrominated biphenyls) on human health.
Since 1941 the School of Public Health has graduated more than 7,000 professional health workers and ranks among the largest of the 24 accredited schools of public health in the United States and Puerto Rico. It is also one of no more than 100 such institutions world-wide. The School of Public Health has continued to emphasize epidemiology and population-based studies of health and illness through multi-disciplinary approaches to community-based health problems and health care delivery while adhering to the basic mission of contributing to the maintenance and improvement of the health of all people by disseminating knowledge, training health professionals and providing advisory and other services to agencies and individuals. Since the 1980s the school has focused on AIDS/HIV, substance abuse, smoking, air pollution, and health gerontology.
Henry Vaughan served as dean of the School of Public Health from its institutional origin until his retirement in 1959. William C. Gibson was named acting dean and served a one-year term. Myron E. Wegman was appointed dean in 1960 and headed the school for fourteen years. Richard A. Remington succeeded Wegman in 1974 and served through 1982. John Kirscht was interim dean from 1982 to 1984. June E. Osborn took the reins in 1984, becoming the first woman to head the school. Richard E. Cornell served as interim dean from 1993 to 1995. In 1995 Noreen Clark, chair of the Department of Health Behavior and Health Education, was named as dean.
Deans of the School of Public Health
1941-1959 Henry F. Vaughan
1959-1960 William C. Gibson (interim)
1960-1974 Myron E. Wegman
1974-1982 Richard A. Remington
1982-1984 John Kirscht (interim)
1984-1993 June E. Osborn
1993-1995 Richard E. Cornell (interim)
1995-2005 Noreen Clark
2005- Kenneth E. Warner
Dean's Records -- (Boxes 1-7, 13-38, 55-63)
Dean Henry F. Vaughan, 1941-1965 (Boxes 1-7)
Dean Myron E. Wegman, 1958-1973 (Boxes 13-24)
Dean Richard Remington, 1974-1981 (Boxes 24-36)
Dean John P. Kirscht, 1982-1984 (Boxes 37-38, 55)
Dean June Osborn, 1984-1989 (Boxes 55-68)
Dean Doreen Clarke, 1995-2004 (Boxes 69-94)
Association of Schools of Public Health --(Boxes 11-12, 39-40, 49-51, 83-88)
Histories/Bylaws -- (Box 1)
Institutes and Inservice Courses -- (Boxes 7-8)
Office Files -- (Boxes 39-54)
Program in Public Health Nursing -- (Boxes 9-10)
Major Subjects
Accreditation -- (Boxes 12, 25, 33, 39, 56)
AIDS -- (Boxes 56-61)
Annual Reports -- (Boxes 1, 13-38, 55-59) (See Also Separate School of Public Health Printed Materials Finding Aid)
Budgets, 1940-1965 -- (Boxes 41-42) (See Also Individual Dean's Annual Files)
Building Construction, 1941-1952 -- (Box 4)
Center for Continuing Education of Public Health Professionals, 1975-1984 -- (Boxes 51, 26-38, 55-56)
Departmental Reviews, 1972-1987 -- (Boxes 53-54)
Executive Committee -- (Boxes 1, 13-38, 52, 55-63)
Kellogg Foundation -- (Boxes 5, 10, 26, 41, 56, 58, 60-61)
National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis -- (Box 6)
PBBs (Polybrominated Biphenyls) -- (Boxes 48, 57)
Public Health Nursing, 1909-1977 -- (Boxes 9-10, 14, 16-18, 24-25, 27-28, 30) (See Also Community Health in Dean's Annual Files)
Tecumseh Community Health Study -- (Boxes 7, 13-17, 19-22, 24, 27, 30)
The records of the School Public Health include Dean's files of Henry F. Vaughan, Myron Wegman, Richard Remington, John Kirscht, June E. Osborn and Noreen M. Clark; files concerning the Association of Schools of Public Health; records of the school's Program in Public Health Nursing; institutes and inservice courses; records regarding school-wide issues and departmental affairs, including accreditation and program reviews; committee and faculty meeting minutes; building construction records; and files relating to state and national public health issues such as PBB contamination, poliomyelitis, and AIDS; including materials concerning public health in Detroit.
Subjects:
AIDS (Disease)--United States.; American Public Health Association.; Association of Schools of Public Health.; Dental public health.; Environmental health.; Epidemiology.; Francis, Thomas, 1900-; Health behavior.; Health education.; Health risk assessment.; Industrial hygiene.; Nurses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Polybrominated biphenyls.; Public health.; Public health--Michigan--Detroit.; Public health nursing.; Public health--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Tecumseh (Mich.)--Statistics, Medical.; Tecumseh Community Health Study.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.; University of Michigan--Students.; W. K. Kellogg Foundation.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Children.; Nursing--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Photographs.; West Physics Building (University of Michigan); Poliomyelitis.; Salk, Jonas, 1914-1995.; School of Public Health Building (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan. Program in Public Health Nursing.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
Contributors:
Clark, Noreen M.; Kirscht, John P.; Osborn, June E., 1937-; Remington, Richard D.; Vaughan, Henry F. (Henry Frieze), 1889-1979; Wegman, Myron E.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Websites.
- Histories/Bylaws
  The Histories/Bylaws series, 1942-1975, includes several articles on the history of public health education at the University of Michigan and a list of items placed in the cornerstone of the School of Public Health Building in 1944. This series also contains the bylaws dealing with the governance of the school and organizational charts detailing the changing departmental and divisional structure over time.
  - circa 1942-1958 (Box 1)
- Dean Henry F. Vaughan, 1940-1967
  The Dean's Files: Henry F. Vaughan, 1941-1967 (primarily 1941-1959), comprise the is divided into five subseries: Annual Reports, Committees, Correspondence, Faculty Correspondence, and Topical Files. Portions of the dean's files have been significantly rearranged in processing the collection. Among the least disturbed from the original order are the Annual Reports and Committees subseries. The annual reports, 1944-1959, are sometimes duplicates of those printed in the President's Annual Report, but they often include more detailed reports of departmental and faculty activities. The Committees subseries, 1941-1967, consists of individual files of minutes for various school and departmental committees. Most of these files are very incomplete; the collection has only limited runs of executive committee and faculty minutes, for example.
  The Correspondence, Faculty Correspondence, and Topical Files subseries represent a substantial rearrangement of the filing system used by the dean's office. In the original office organizing scheme all materials in these three subseries were in one alphabetical subseries filed geographically by origin or destination of the letter or memorandum. For example, correspondence relating to the planning and construction of the school's building was filed under "Battle Creek" because the architect was located there. Because this filing system hardly seemed intuitive for researchers, a new arrangement has been created breaking what had formerly been a single run of correspondence into three subseries: Correspondence, Faculty Correspondence, and Topical Files.
  The first two subseries can be seen as paired; one (Correspondence) dealing primarily with developments in public health outside the University of Michigan School of Public Health, and the other (Faculty Correspondence) dealing mostly with the internal workings of the school.
  - Annual Reports
    - 1944-1959, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Academic Rank and Promotions, 1959 (Box 1)
    - Development, 1950-1958 (Box 1)
    - Executive, 1941-1944; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Faculty Meetings, 1941-1947 (Box 1)
    - Field Experience, 1955-1967 (Box 1)
    - Health Services, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
    - Inservice Instruction, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
    - Inter-Cultural Relations, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Research, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - Service, 1953-1959 (Box 1)
    - Social Sciences in Public Health, 1959-1964 (Box 1)
    - Study of Comprehensive Reports, 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1941-1959
    The Correspondence subseries, comprising 1.6 linear feet of material, is arranged chronologically and covers the years from 1941 to 1959. This is the most diffuse subseries as it contains much information on developments in the field of public health, Vaughan's professional activities, and the school's work with international, national, state, and local health agencies.
    - 1941-August 1944, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - September 1944-1959, 17 folders (Box 2)
  - Faculty Correspondence, 1941-1959
    The Faculty Correspondence, 1941-1959, runs one linear foot and is arranged alphabetically by individual faculty member. This correspondence relates primarily to the governance of the school and to the activities of the faculty member or the department in which he or she served. For example, the H. E. Miller correspondence contains much material on the school's extension program and the many institutes and inservice courses the school sponsored. The Ella McNeil files include information on the public health nursing program.
    - Beeuwkes, Adelia, 1944-1956 (Box 3)
    - Buck, Carl, 1949-1950 (Box 3)
    - Coggeshall, Lowell, 1941-1946 (Box 3)
    - Connally, Mary T., 1943-1946 (Box 3)
    - Francis, Thomas, 1941-1959; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Getting, Vlado, 1956-1959 (Box 3)
    - Gibson, William, 1951-1959 (Box 3)
    - Hall, Marguerite (Box 3)
    - Hanlon, John, 1949-1951 (Box 3)
    - McNeil, Ella, 1941-1959; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Miller, H.E., 1941-1959; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Ramsey, George H (Box 3)
    - Rugen, Mabel E., 1941-1958; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Selby, C.D., 1950-1951 (Box 3)
    - Sinai, Nathan, 1941-1959; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Smith, Donald C., 1955 (Box 3)
    - Sundwall, John, 1943-1947 (Box 3)
    - Tiedman, Walter, 1950-1951 (Box 3)
    - Velz, C.J., 1949-1959 (Box 3)
  - Topical Files, 1940-1959
    The Vaughan Topical Files, 1940-1959 subseries consists of correspondence, reports and other related material about a particular subject, program, or activity. The files are arranged alphabetically by topic and there-under chronologically. Among the significant topical files are Building Construction, which contains correspondence, drawings, and blueprints relating to the construction and expansion of the School of Public Health building; Division of Biological Sciences, consisting of early minutes of the Division; Hospital Administration Program; Institute of Industrial Health; W. K. Kellogg Foundation, concerning Vaughan's service on the Foundation Board and the Foundation's grants to the school; State Council of Health, which Vaughan chaired for a number of years; and the Tecumseh Community Health Study. The Course Outline files will be of particular interest to the researcher examining classroom content of public health education. The course descriptions, outlines, and lecture notes cover the years from 1943 to 1959 in an incomplete, yet informative way. The Topical Files also include newspaper clippings and photographs.
    - Alumni Surveys (Box 4)
    - APWA Medical Assistance Research Project, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Building Construction/Expansion, 1941-1952; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Building Construction/Expansion, 1956-1960
      - Blueprints (Box 4)
      - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Press Releases and Clippings (Box 4)
      - Prospectus (Box 4)
    - Cancer Research Grant, 1949-1954 (Box 4)
    - Children's Fund of Michigan, 1944 (Box 4)
    - Course Outlines, ca., 1943-1959; 6 folders (Box 4)
    - Curriculum Conferences
      - 1952-1953, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1960, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Daley, Sir Allen, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Delta Omega, 1941-1952; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Dining Room, 1944-1947 (Box 4)
    - Division of Biological Sciences, 1950-1953; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Emerson, Haven, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    - Enrollment Statistics, 1941-1950; 1960 (Box 4)
    - Faculty Members (lists of) (Box 5)
    - Field Training, 1945 (Box 5)
    - Ford Foundation Grant Application, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Heart Disease Teaching Grant, 1949-1952 (Box 5)
    - Hospital Administration Program, 1946-1959; 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Institute of Industrial Health, 1950-1959; 6 folders (Box 5)
    - Institute of Social Welfare, 1947-1952 (Box 5)
    - Inter-American Conference, 1943 (Box 5)
    - Kellogg Foundation, 1940-1947; 7 folders
      - Darling, George (Box 5)
    - Kellogg, John H. and W.K., 1943; 1953; 1955 (Box 5)
    - Library, 1943-1945 (Box 5)
    - Maternal and Child Care Grant, 1958-1959 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Community Health Project, circa 1940-1941; 4 reports (Box 6)
    - National Conference on Public Health Training, 1958 (Box 6)
    - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis (March of Dimes) (Box 6)
    - NIH "Shannon Memo,", 1959 (Box 6)
    - National Sanitation Foundation, 1948-1955; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1945-1955; 6 folders (Box 6)
    - "Next Steps" Conference, 1956 (Box 6)
    - Photographs
      - SPH Building, 1943 (Box 6)
      - Old Physical Laboratory (Box 6)
      - Faculty, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Students (Box 6)
      - Health Posters (negatives only), circa 1944 (Box 6)
    - Radiological Safety Department, 1951-1954 (Box 6)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1941-1945; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Sanitary Engineering Building, 1946 (Box 7)
    - Sloss Loyalty Cases, 1952 (Box 7)
    - State Council of Health, 1941-1955; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - State and Local Health Needs, 1948-1949 (Box 7)
    - Student Survey, 1952 (Box 7)
    - Study of Artificially Induced Immunity, 1958 (Box 7)
    - Tecumseh Community Health Study, 1957-1959; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Television Committee, 1953 (Box 7)
    - Undergraduate Program, 1949-1951; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - USPHS Post-War Training Committee, 1944-1945 (Box 7)
- Institutes and Inservice Courses, 1942-1957
  Beginning in 1942, the School of Public Health sponsored a series of professional conferences whose records comprise the Institutes and Inservice Courses series. The materials in this series span the years from 1942 to 1957 and comprise 1.4 linear feet. The records relating to these institutes and conferences are mainly programs, planning documents, and proceedings. Many of these courses were special wartime training programs. The series is arranged chronologically with individual citations for those institutes or conferences which have published proceedings in the collection.
  - 1942
    - General (Box 7)
    - Hotel and Restaurant Owners and Managers (Box 7)
    - Milk Pasteurization Plants (Box 7)
  - 1943
    - Industrial Hygiene for Safety Personnel (Box 7)
  - 1944
    - Dental Health Economics (Box 7)
    - Milk Sanitation (Box 7)
    - Post-War Epidemiology (Box 7)
    - Recent Developments in Medical/Nursing Care (Box 7)
    - Veterans Rehabilitation (Box 7)
  - 1945
    - Environmental Control and Industrial Processes (Box 8)
    - Evaluation of Public Health Practice (Box 8)
    - Public Relation, Staff Education, and Community Health Education (Box 8)
    - Water Works Personnel (Box 8)
  - 1946
    - Conference on Housing (Box 8)
    - Health Conference for Public Officials (Box 8)
    - National Conference on Local Health Units (Box 8)
    - Preventive Medicine and Health Economics (Box 8)
    - Relation of Nutrition to Maternal Health (Box 8)
  - 1947
    - Evaluation of Dental Caries Technique (Box 8)
    - Food Handling (Box 8)
    - Garbage and Refuse Collection and Disposal (Box 8)
    - Health of the School Child (Box 8)
  - 1948
    - Cancer Services (Box 8)
  - 1949
    - Plumbing Problems (Box 8)
  - 1950
    - Plumbing Problems (Box 8)
  - 1951
    - Water Works Problems (Box 8)
  - 1952